A Finding Aid to the Charles Schucker Papers, 1934-2001, in the Archives of American Art AAA.schuchar
Archives of American Art
Charles Schucker Papers
1934-2001
AAA.schuchar
Archives of American Art
1.2 Linear feet
The papers of New York abstract painter and educator Charles Schucker measure 1.2 linear and date from 1934 to 2001. Schucker's career as a painter is documented by biographical material, letters, writings, subject files, printed material, artwork, and photographs.
Schucker, Charles L.
Biographical/Historical note
Charles L. Schucker (1908-1998), an abstract painter known for poured oil paintings on unprimed canvases, began his career in Chicago with the WPA before moving to New York City in 1946. He was also an educator and taught at the Pratt Institute in Brooklyn, New York for nearly 30 years.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Lent for microfilming in 1971 by Charles Schucker and later donated with additional audio and video recordings in August 2011 by Carrie Schucker, the artist's daughter.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The papers dated from 1934 to 1969 are available on 35mm microfilm reels 80-81 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. While most microfilmed items dated 1969 or earlier can be located in the papers, there are a few exceptions. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid may not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of New York abstract painter and educator Charles Schucker measure 1.2 linear and date from 1934 to 2001. Schucker's career as a painter is documented by biographical material, letters, writings, subject files, printed material, artwork, and photographs.
Biographical material includes a video recording of a memorial tribute. Letters mostly relate to business arrangements with galleries and institutions. Among Schucker's writings are 9 notebooks, some of which include notes from his study abroad. Writings about Schucker include an unpublished manuscript by Valerie Velasquez Louzonis in which she discusses his childhood, travels, and his start as an artist. Subject files touch upon his association with Pratt Institute, Katonah Museum of Art, Yaddo, various galleries, his work with the Chicago WPA, and his friendship with Morris Louis. Over 60 years of artistic work are documented in exhibition catalogs and announcements. Artwork and sketchbooks from the 1930s and 1940s offer a glimpse of his earlier style of drawing.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1938, 1984-1999 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Letters, 1937-2001 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1934-1998 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Subject Files, circa 1940-1999 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1930s-1990s (Boxes 1-2; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork and Sketchbooks, 1930s-1940s (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1951-circa 1980s (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
Federal Art Project (Ill.); Katonah Museum of Art.; Louis, Morris, 1912-1962; Louzonis, Valerie Velasquez; Pratt Institute; Yaddo (Artist's colony); Drawings; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting, Modern--20th century--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Video recordings
- Biographical Materials, 1984-1999; 1938; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes one videocassette recording of Schucker's memorial service, his marriage certificate and a citation from the Brooklyn borough president. Also included are personal and professional financial records.
  - "Remembering Charles Schucker at the Studio, February 1, 1998", 1998 February 1; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificate and Citation, 1938; 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Financial Records, 1981-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Letters, 1937-2001; Series 2; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains mostly incoming letters regarding business with galleries and institutions.
  Arrangement note
  Additional letters and correspondence can be found in series 4: subject files.
  - Letters, 1937-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Writings, 1939-1998; Series 3; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains 9 notebooks from the 1930s to the 1990s. Included are a research notebook from the 1930s with a pencil sketch on back page of Chicago's skyline along Lake Michigan, 4 notebooks about travels to Europe in the 1930s and 1940s, and anatomy notes from Rockefeller University circa 1930s.
  Writings about Schucker include a 44 page unpublished manuscript by Valerie Velasquez Louzonis.
  - Notebooks Volumes 1-2, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notebooks Volume 3, 1934-1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks Volume 4, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notebooks Volumes 5-8, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notebooks Volume 9, 1970s; 1950s; 1954 January (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Anatomy Notes, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lists, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Writings about Schucker, 1939-1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Subject Files, circa 1940-1999; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Subject files contain letters, correspondence, agreements, sales contracts, some press releases and clippings, and photographs of works of art. Also found are 2 videocassettes and 1 sound cassette. The Chicago file contains a civil service job application. Schucker was a member of Yaddo; that file includes a guest list, letters, by-laws, notices, and profiles of prospective members.
  This is series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Aaron Gallery, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chicago, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chicago WPA, 1999; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gallery Camino Real, 1979-1980s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ann Goodman, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Katonah Art Gallery, 1965; 1980; 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Morris Louis, 1994; undated; Includes1 videocassette (VHS) and 1 sound cassette (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pratt Institute Exhibition, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Princeton Gallery of Fine Arts, 1980-1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Print Artery, Ltd., 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Yaddo, 1970-1999 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Printed Material, 1930s-1990s; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Printed material relates to Schucker's artwork and includes group exhibition catalogs, invitations, announcements, and clippings. Also found are items related to the centennial exhibition for the Brooklyn Bridge.
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Invitations and Announcements, 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 26-28)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Invitations and Announcements, 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Clippings, 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Artwork and Sketchbooks, 1930s-1940s; Series 6; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Artwork includes 3 pen and ink sketches with some color wash as well as 2 small sketchbooks in both pencil and pen.
  - Drawings, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Photographs, 1951-circa 1980s; Series 7; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Photographs are of Schucker with his artwork.
  - Photographs, 1951-circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 7)